Socialist Labor Party Pamphlets
Socialist Labor Party Pamphlets
1913-1942
Socialist Labor Party.
0.5 linear ft.
Collection of 56 pamphlets issued by the Socialist Labor Party; topics include unemployment, low wages, capitalism, fascism, war/peace, strikes and anti-semitism. Also, several city and state party platforms.
3298890
Biographical History
The Socialist Labor Party (SLP) was established in 1876 as the Workingmen's Party but renamed the next year. It is the oldest socialist political party in the United States and the second oldest socialist party in the world. It ran the first socialist presidential campaign in 1892, and fielded national tickets in every presidential campaign through 1976.
According to the party's website, their goal is "a classless society based on collective ownership and control of the industries and social services, these to be administered in the interests of all society through a Socialist Industrial Union government composed of democratically elected representatives from all the industries and services of the land. Production would be carried on for use instead of profit."
Daniel DeLeon (1852-1914), author of three of the pamphlets, was an American socialist newspaper editor, politician, Marxist theoretician, and trade union organizer, and was a leading figure in the Socialist Labor Party of America.
Arnold Petersen (1885-1976), author of two of the pamphlets, was the party's National Secretary for more than 50 years.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Socialist Labor Party Pamphlets consist of 56 pamphlets put out by the party on a range of topics relevant to their ideology and goals. Topics covered include unemployment, low wages, capitalism, fascism, war/peace, strikes and anti-semitism. The collection also includes the Louisville city platform, and state platforms for New York and Illinois.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by title.
Related Material
has extensive holdings relating to Socialism, Communism and American radicalism, including a collection of
American radical ephemera
please see for a full listing. For cataloged books and periodicals, including New Masses and Partisan Review, please consult.
Subject and Genre Headings
Radicalism; Politics, government and public administration; De Leon, Daniel, 1852-1914.; Petersen, Arnold, 1885-1976.; Socialist Labor Party.; Communism -- United States.; Labor movement -- United States.; Political parties--Platforms.; Radicalism -- United States.; Socialism -- United States.; United States -- Economic conditions -- 1961-1971.; Pamphlets.; Propaganda.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Originals in box 2 are restricted due to condition. Researchers are requested to use the photocopies in Box 1.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Inventory
- Pamphlets (photocopies)
  - Abolish capitalism!, 1932 (Box 1)
  - An address to the voters of the state of Massachusetts (Box 1)
  - Anti-semitism: cause and cure (Box 1)
  - Atomic power:promise or menace? (Box 1)
  - Capitalist unionism, 1925? (Box 1)
  - The C.I.O., by Daniel de Leon, after 1937 (Box 1)
  - City of Louisville platform, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Civil liberties: an American heritage, after 1942 (Box 1)
  - Collapse of capitalism, 1927; letter of acceptance of Jeremiah D. Crowley, Socialist Labor candidate for vice-president (Box 1)
  - The democracy of socialism (Box 1)
  - Do we have a democracy? (Box 1)
  - Fascism (Box 1)
  - Fascism, or industrial feudalism… (Box 1)
  - The fascist menace (without subheadings) (Box 1)
  - The fascist menace (with subheadings) (Box 1)
  - Illinois state platform, 1938? (Box 1)
  - Industrial union government, 1933? (Box 1)
  - Industrial unionism, by Daniel de Leon, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Is labor a commodity?, 1938; 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Is Socialism un-American?, 1940? (Box 1)
  - The labor draft, 1940? (Box 1)
  - The labor draft: step to industrial slavery (Box 1)
  - The machine and unemployment (Box 1)
  - New York state platform, 1947? (Box 1)
  - 1944 platform (Box 1)
  - No jobs -- why?, 1940? (Box 1)
  - Outlawing strikes (Box 1)
  - Own your jobs! (Box 1)
  - The police and the right of revolution (Box 1)
  - Political gangsterism, by Arnold Petersen (Box 1)
  - Post-war crisis, 1940-1946 (Box 1)
  - Poverty can be abolished (Box 1)
  - The program for peace, security and freedom, 1952 (Box 1)
  - The race problem (Box 1)
  - Re Australia, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Significance of the ballot (Box 1)
  - Socialism: champion of civilized principles (Box 1)
  - Socialism and the flag, by Daniel de Leon (Box 1)
  - The Socialist Labor Party vs. the Socialist Party (Box 1)
  - Socialism now!...or chaos (Box 1)
  - Stop peacetime conscription! (Box 1)
  - Stop peacetime conscription! (Box 1)
  - Survival is the issue! (Box 1)
  - There can be no peace without socialism (Box 1)
  - Tom Mooney and the class struggle (Box 1)
  - The two party hoax (Box 1)
  - Unemployment (Box 1)
  - Unemployment…why? (Box 1)
  - The "union label" by Arnold Petersen (Box 1)
  - The value of labor laws (Box 1)
  - War (Box 1)
  - Watch your liberties! (Box 1)
  - What is socialism? (Box 1)
  - What means this strike? (Box 1)
  - What Socialism means (Box 1)
  - Whither society?, 2 copies (Box 1)
- Pamphlets (originals)
  Originals of the pamphlets are restricted due to condition. Researchers are requested to use the photocopies in Box 1.
  - A-Z (Box 2)